Why are there more tornadoes in the
United States than anywhere else on
Earth? By a lot. And nearly all of them
happen right here. To make a tornado,
you need four ingredients. Number one,
warm, wet air. This flows into the
plains from the Gulf. Two, warm, dry air
pulled across the plains by a jet
stream. That hot, dry air forms a cap,
keeping that wet air close to the
ground. Ingredient three is these
perpendicular winds moving at different
speeds that act like a blender, causing
the wind in the middle to rotate. Which
is actually fine until you add
ingredient four, superdense, cold, dry
air that flows in like a bulldozer
busting through that cap causing that
warm, wet air to shoot upward. Sometimes
over 160 kilometers per hour rapidly
forming these gigantic storm clouds. And
then, as that spinning air races upward,
it's tilted into a vertically spinning
storm. That hot, dry air is still
flowing in, but now it's rapidly being
cooled by rain causing it to plummet
toward the ground, but the warm, wet air
down there is still spiraling it right
back up into the storm. And all that is
forming a tornado. And it's important to
understand these ingredients because
Tornado Alley is moving. To find out
why, subscribe.